Jack: How is data stored?
Data storage allows data to be stored
on a computer when it powers down.
All data in a computer is stored as a
number, but not a conventional number.
Conventional numbers use ten
different digits but binary
numbers use two digits only.
Data is converted into binary digital form
using two digits 1 and 0 to be stored.
A bit is the smallest unit of
data representing a single value.
A byte is eight binary digits long.
Leah: The conventional numbers
0-8 translate into 0, 1, 10,
11, 100, 101, 110, 111 and 1000.
So when data is stored even letters become
numbers, for example the words in a book
would be stored one byte per letter.
Photographs are also converted to
numbers that indicate the location,
colour and brightness of each pixel.
Jack: Storage and memory is often
measured in megabytes and gigabytes and
even terabytes, however, as units of
data measurement begin to grow so does
the amount of data collected and stored.
Binary data is primarily stored
on the hard disk drive [HDD].
In addition to this storage can be
on SSD flash drives and memory cards.
With this type of storage, the
binary numbers are stored as
a series of electrical charges
within NAND flash chips.
Leah: To store data regardless of its
form, users, need to use storage devices.
These will be either 'direct area'
storage or 'network based' storage.
Direct area storage is directly
attached to a computer.
It can offer back up services or can be
used as storage in conjunction with a
program that may be memory intensive.
Network based storage allows more
than one computer to access it
through the network making it better
for sharing and collaborating.
It may be off site or even cloud based.